We'll be right back.
We're a denominational family.
So I just wanted to say thank you
for like allowing me the privilege of doing that.
And I listened to Pastor Sam's message.
So I know that you all were blessed that I was,
not blessed that I was gone,
but blessed that he was here.
And so just so thankful that we have community partners
and gospel partners and kingdom partners in our city
that don't just care about their church,
but care about the church.
I'm so thankful.
And Sam is one of many that I would call on
at any time of the day to just support me,
encourage me and support us and encourage us.
And while I'm on the topic of me hearing Pastor Sam's message,
I had a conversation with a friend of mine
who's been at our church for years.
And he was asking about like getting access to our messages.
So I'm just gonna plug this really quick
in case you did not know.
We have a podcast channel.
You can find us on Spotify.
You can listen to me on two times speed
if you missed me or missed Sam.
That's what I did.
Sam, I think I was like 1.75 on the way to the airport.
And it was great.
So it's there if you need it.
It's there if you wanna share it
with your friends and your neighbors.
But Sam kicked off a two parts,
part two of our eight week series
on community and service
by reminding us that serving is,
it's intended to come from a place of love and not duty.
It's intended to come from out of the overflow
of a full and loved heart
and not just in order to impress God
or to get something from others.
Service is a spiritual discipline.
It is, you know, when I grew up in church,
the only spiritual disciplines there were
were prayer and Bible reading.
There's so much more to the Christian faith than that.
And out of that, we talked about things
that happened because of that.
But service is a discipline
that we choose to do as Christians.
And it's a discipline at the very intersection
of loving God with all of your heart, soul, mind,
and strength and loving your neighbor as yourself.
And so my hope and prayer
throughout these next four weeks
is that we keep our eyes focused on that intersection
of loving God and loving our neighbor
because service is something that can easily happen
just focused on loving our neighbor
and forgetting about the root of God's love for us.
So this morning, we're gonna continue this series
by looking at one of the most profound acts of service
recorded for us from the life of Jesus.
Let's pray and we'll get started.
Father in heaven,
thank you for your example.
Thank you for sending Jesus, the incarnate one,
who can model for us what it looks like
to follow you with flesh and blood,
with dirty feet and calloused hands.
You didn't just send us your word from heaven,
but you sent us your son
who became word in the flesh,
dwelt among us.
God, may we look to him as our example this morning.
May we learn from his example.
May we be reminded of the love
that the incarnation truly is towards us.
God, we need you to remind us
of how much we are loved,
how much we are forgiven,
of how much grace is available to us.
Speak to us today by your Holy Spirit
for your glory and for our good
and for the good of our neighbor.
It's in Jesus' name I pray, amen.
How many fans of the show The Office
are in the room this morning?
Okay, a good number of us.
We like The Office.
I have an illustration that I want to use.
Whoa, back that up, back it up, back it up real quick.
You jump into the punchline before it's there.
Marissa and I love The Office,
and I think this is a helpful illustration,
but I'm afraid for those of you
that don't watch The Office, you might lose me.
So try and stay focused.
It is a hyperbolic satire,
and so just try and stick with me for just a second.
In season four, episode one,
Michael Scott hits one of his employees
named Meredith Palmer in the parking lot
with his vehicle as he is riding into work.
And he hits her in the car,
he hits her with his car,
and then he helps her get to the hospital,
and it's at the hospital when the office finds out
that she may have rabies.
Yes, so bad day turns to worse.
She gets hit by a car in the parking lot,
and now she may or may not have rabies.
And Michael Scott's dealing with all of the mixed emotions
and guilt of being the one that hit her with the car
and also never wanting to be wrong,
and so trying to justify all of the things
that have happened.
And with a mix of complicated emotions
and motivations, guilt,
and the thing about Michael Scott
is even when he's acting like a total buffoon,
you can see deep down inside
that he actually does care.
And so with this mixed emotions
of kindness, compassion, and also guilt,
and also just a desire to be praised,
he organizes the, here we go,
Michael Scott's Dunder Mifflin,
Scranton Meredith Palmer Memorial Celebrity Rabies Awareness
Pro-Am Fun Run Race for the Cure.
As you can see the succinct title on the T-shirt,
he organizes this very long titled race
in order to raise money for rabies,
a disease that has already been cured.
So, although the plot of this episode,
as with the entire show,
is just blatant hyperbolic satire,
I think it reveals something that is typically true
of human beings as it relates to the idea of serving others.
And that is we come to service
with this mixed bag of motivations.
We come to service with this idea
of wanting in some ways
to kind of earn favor before God.
We wanna demonstrate to God and to others
that we are a person that is worthy of praise
because we are willing to sacrifice and serve others.
Sometimes we do it out of guilt,
out of a, I'm gonna pay off the bad things I've done
with the good things that I've done.
And service is this thing where it's really easy
for us to do the right thing for the wrong reasons.
Anybody resonate with that idea this morning?
Either out of guilt or regret
or a desire to make a name for ourselves
before God and others,
we can easily make a habit of doing the right thing
for the wrong reasons,
which will not give us the results
that Jesus is wanting for us
when he invites us to serve.
He invites us to serve
because in truly serving him
out of a love for God
and a love for our neighbor,
we will experience the abundant life
that glorifies God and that gives us peace.
But there's a way in which we can pursue service
without getting those results.
And so what I wanna do this morning
is I wanna look at an example
of Jesus serving his disciples
and doing so in such a way
that sets an example for us,
that teaches us what genuine kingdom service looks like
and it equips us moving forward
to serve in the same way that Jesus did.
So if you have your Bibles,
you wanna turn to John chapter 13.
John chapter 13 is gonna be our text this morning
and in it, we will see Jesus set an example,
but it's also not just him setting an example,
it's him giving an object lesson to his disciples.
It's intended both to teach them something
intellectually, emotionally,
and also send them out in the future
with the same type of service that Jesus serves them.
One where we do the right things for the right reasons.
And the curriculum that we're following,
the focus on this week
is the idea of serving in hiddenness.
Like we start this discipline of service in hiddenness
because when we can do it sacrificially for no praise,
for no pride, for no other acceptance,
for no other benefit
other than just to sacrificially serve,
if we build our service on that,
it is in the hidden places where we serve
that we can be formed into a person
that can go out and serve in the public square
and do it for the right reason.
That make sense?
All right, so John chapter 13, starting in verse one,
says, it was just before the Passover festival.
Jesus knew that the hour had come for him
to leave this world and go to the Father.
I love that idea that this is right before
he's about to go to the cross.
And it says he knew the hour had come.
What hour had come?
The hour for him to go to the cross?
No, he says the hour for him to leave this world
and go to his Father.
Like even in the midst of him going to the cross,
his focus is on reunion with the Father.
His focus is on the kingdom to come.
Having loved his own who were in the world,
he loved them to the end.
The evening meal was in progress
and the devil had already prompted Judas,
the son of Simon Iscariot,
to betray Jesus.
Jesus knew that the Father had put all things
under his power and that he had come from God
and was returning to God.
He had this kingdom perspective.
And because of that, it says,
he got up from the meal.
He took off his outer clothing.
He wrapped a towel around his waist.
After that, he poured water into a basin
and he began to wash his disciples' feet,
drying them with the towel that was wrapped around him.
Jumping to verse 12, it says,
when he had finished washing their feet,
he put on his clothes and returned to his place.
And he said to his disciples,
do you understand what I have done for you?
You call me teacher and Lord and rightly so,
for this is what I am.
Now that I, your Lord and teacher,
have washed your feet,
you should also wash one another's feet.
I have set for you an example
that you should do as I have done for you.
Very truly, I tell you,
no servant is greater than his master,
nor is a messenger greater than the one who sent him.
Now that you know these things,
you will be blessed if you do them.
So the disciples who are participating
in the Passover meal with Jesus
just hours before he will be crucified
are doing something really interesting.
We don't have it in the context in John,
but we have it in the context of Luke.
Luke records that during this very dinner,
the disciples whom Jesus loved behind closed doors
who are celebrating the Passover feast
that's supposed to focus their attention
on God's deliverance in their lives,
they are in a debate
over who is the greatest among them in the kingdom.
Sound like Christians?
Right?
So they're debating over
who is the greatest among them in the kingdom,
and I think that it's in that context
that we have to put Jesus doing this object lesson,
this parable for them.
He is showing them the definition to that question,
the answer to the question
of who is the greatest among you,
and what does it look like
to be the greatest among people in the kingdom?
And it's not that they aren't willing to serve, right?
The disciples have followed Jesus
for three years at this point,
sacrificially giving up so much,
giving up their careers and their life,
and they have followed Jesus.
They are willing to serve.
They know Jesus.
They know who he is.
They know what he's about.
It's not that they're opposed to sacrificial service.
It's that they're primarily focused right now
on the rewards that they will receive
for the things that they've given up.
It's in this very moment that they are like,
yeah, we'll serve.
We'll give our lives for this kingdom,
but what do we get in return?
Just like Michael Scott,
and like most of us in the room,
even in our willingness to serve others,
oftentimes somewhere deep down inside of us,
we are thinking about how we might benefit from it.
And it's in that moment
that the incarnate Son of God
models for them what true service
in the kingdom of God looks like.
He does the unspeakable,
a service that I read scholars say
Jewish slaves wouldn't even typically perform.
So this is a cultural thing that would happen
because they walked the streets
that were filled with dirt, mud, and human feces.
Oftentimes they would have Gentile servants
waiting at the door to wash the feet
before you go to a meal
because you don't wanna sit at the table
where you are reclining with your feet
next to the head of the person you're sitting next to
with feet that are disgusting.
And so the servants would do this.
And apparently for this reason,
and I'm guessing that Jesus made sure
that it wasn't organized this way,
nobody washed the disciples' feet.
And it's in the midst of the dinner,
Jesus gets up and he lives out a parable
about service in the kingdom of God
to his disciples who are debating
who is the greatest among them.
Are we tracking?
And it's impossible for us to wrap our minds
how culturally shocking this action would have been.
I racked my brain for the last few days
trying to come up with an illustration
that meets our cultural expectations
where we can imagine how audacious it would be
that Jesus did this thing.
And I just didn't have one.
I don't think there is one
that really illustrates for us
what it is that Jesus is doing right now.
And he's not just doing it for his faithful disciples.
He does it to Peter,
who he knows is about to betray him three times.
And he does it to Judas,
who he knows is the reason he is about to be killed.
And what's interesting to me is later,
Jesus tells them,
somebody's gonna betray me tonight.
And they're like, who is it?
So like Jesus so loved Judas in the midst of this
that there wasn't a passive aggressive,
like scrubbing his feet a little bit harder, right?
Like the whole room was like,
who is gonna betray you?
Jesus is lovingly washing the feet of his enemy,
the person that's going to betray him,
his best friend that's going to deny him three times.
And there is nothing in this for Jesus.
He's behind closed doors.
The action is done to a group of people
that have already given up everything to follow him.
He isn't doing this for any other reason
but to teach them and to equip them,
to teach them how much he loves them,
how deeply he is,
everything in him is for them.
He does this so that they get this idea in their bones
because they are about to have to,
they are about to be invited
to give up everything for him.
And you can't do that out of a place
of not knowing how loved you are from God.
So Jesus models this for him.
He teaches them so that they can understand it.
And then he sets an example for them
so that they will do it.
I love verse 17.
It's gonna be the framework for the rest of our talk.
He says, now that you know these things,
you will be blessed if you do them.
Knowing is this experiential understanding,
this learning a lesson
from what Jesus has done before them.
We have to learn a lesson
about how much Jesus loves us,
about the service that he has done
in laying down his life for us
before we can ever go out
and serve others in the same way.
So he says, learn from me first this lesson
of what it means to serve in the kingdom.
Know these things deep inside your bones
and then once you understand this,
do not serve before you understand
how much I have served you.
Come first to the table to see,
to experience and to know how much I love you
and then go out and do it for others also.
So first, let's look at this idea of knowing,
of learning, of teaching.
And teach is the word I have in my outline,
but it's probably not the best terminology here
because I think Jesus is performing
this act of sacrificial love
to help them understand both intellectually,
which is the idea of teach,
but also on an experiential level,
how much he loves them.
This is an object lesson of Christ's love for them
and for us.
It is intended to help us grasp at a guttural level
how high and how wide and how deep
is the love of Christ for us.
And if we truly learn this lesson,
we will serve others in the very same way
because our cup is full.
Genuine kingdom service comes out of the overflow
of the love that we have received from Jesus.
And he knows that as sinful, selfish,
and broken people living in a broken world,
we are typically preoccupied with serving ourselves.
We are typically preoccupied with this scarcity mindset.
It's the fear that comes in in Genesis 3,
the sweat of the brow,
there isn't going to be enough for me and my people.
And Jesus knows that the tendency of the human heart
is to operate out of a scarcity mindset.
And I think the reason oftentimes
we either choose not to serve others sacrificially
or choose to serve others
in order to get something out of it
is because we operate out of this scarcity mindset.
We're looking for love, we're longing for love.
And it's interesting to me,
if you interact with people
that are like emotionally unhealthy,
like outwardly doing things
where you can like Michael Scott, right?
He's like obvious to everyone around him
that he's doing this for the wrong reasons.
When you, typically my experience
is when I have interactions with people like that
where you could just blatantly tell.
It's like, oh, you're doing this for you,
not for anybody else.
It's been my experience
that those people often were not loved well
as children or even currently,
that they're operating out of this scarcity mindset.
They want others to love them so bad
that they're acting in this unhealthy and bad way,
but deep down inside, they're crying for love.
And I think what Jesus is doing here
is he's teaching his disciples
that you are already far more loved
than you ever dare hope.
And if you can get this in your bones,
then you will be able to serve others
out of a, not a scarcity mindset,
but an abundance mindset
that you have more than enough love to give to others.
You have more than enough forgiveness to give to others.
You have more than enough grace to extend to others
because grace has been extended to you
over and over and over again.
We did this marriage content with Marissa a few years back
and I love the illustration they used.
I'll never forget about it.
They talked about how meeting each other's expectations
is really helpful for good communication.
And when unmet expectations haven't been communicated,
it's like you're stepping on your partner's air hose.
And so I don't know if you've ever been
in this type of interaction with a spouse before
or a partner where they're acting out
and you're like, whoa, like that's crazy.
But like they're acting out
because they're desperate for something
that you haven't given them.
Maybe they haven't communicated it,
but it doesn't matter.
They need something from you and they don't have it.
And that thing that they don't have
feels like it's killing them.
And so when somebody steps on an air hose,
actions get pretty desperate, right?
And I think oftentimes when we serve out of the wrong reason
or we don't serve at all,
it's because we feel like we've gotta get ours for us.
And Jesus here in this example is saying,
you already have all that you need in me.
I have given you all that you need
to be full and to serve others.
We need to meditate on this reality,
actually learn this truth experientially
so that we have this abundant mindset
that we know we have more than enough to give to others.
I love how 1 John puts it, 1 John chapter four.
This is one of the disciples who was sitting at this table
who had learned this lesson experientially.
He said, this is how God showed us his love among us.
He sent his one and only son into the world
so that we might live through him.
This is love, not that we have loved God,
but that he has loved us and sent his son
as an atoning sacrifice for our sins.
We have to first and foremost realize
how much God has loved us in Jesus.
I think John experientially learned this lesson
over the three years of Christ's ministry, yes,
but I think there's no more potent opportunity
for him to learn this lesson than in this upper room
when Jesus stood up to do the most audacious thing
that any rabbi would ever think to do.
John knew in his bones that Jesus loved him
and because of that, he was willing to serve others.
Because he learned that lesson,
he was set up to serve others in the very same way.
And I would suggest to us this morning
that Jesus has invited us to serve others
in the same way that he has served us,
but before we can do that,
we have to get this truth in our bones.
At an experiential level,
we have to learn the love of God for us
and it's so easy to forget.
I know this is like,
you guys are like,
okay, you spent 20 minutes telling us Jesus loves us.
Can we move on to something else?
No, we can't.
We cannot move on past this
until we get it in our bones
and we have an enemy that roars around
like a lion seeking to devour us and destroy us.
And I think the primary place that he attacks us
is this reality.
You are not love.
You are not welcomed.
You have done too much.
You have walked away too far.
Do you know what you've done?
Do you know where you've been?
Do you know who you are?
And Jesus says,
I stood up from the table
and I washed Judas' feet.
I love you.
No matter how much we've walked away,
no matter how much we've abandoned Jesus,
he keeps extending his grace.
He wants us to know at an experiential level
how much he loves us
so that we can serve others out of an abundance mindset.
So to get really practical here on this section,
a couple of things that I would encourage you
to think about doing.
The first is I would encourage you
to think about reading John chapter 13 this week
a few times with an imaginative reading process,
kind of this Lectio Divina.
We've talked about it in the past,
but like do your best to just sit quietly
in a space where you have time and space
to just like be by yourself,
which I know for some of us who have toddlers
is next to impossible,
but find a way.
And think about putting yourself in the room,
sitting around the table,
and just read this passage.
Think about the reality of how much God truly loves you.
Read it again and again and again
until it gets deep into your soul,
until it's not just words on a page,
but it is a reality that Jesus is doing this for you.
Second thing I would encourage you to do
is consider showing up
to the threefold communion service.
I know for many of us,
that's like uncomfortable and weird
and very not culturally relevant,
but I will tell you from firsthand experience,
it's one of the most powerful ways
to truly just like learn this lesson.
It's an embodied spiritual practice.
We are whole human beings,
and oftentimes we handle discipleship
just in our heads.
And like I think Corey said this last week,
it's one thing to wash somebody else's feet.
You wanna learn this lesson
about how much Jesus loves you.
You let another sinner wash your feet
and then heighten that feeling that you have
to the point of Jesus,
the God who made you,
who put breath in your lungs
doing that very action to you.
It will totally reframe how you think about this.
So consider that.
Kingdom service looks like
first knowing fully what Jesus has done for you
and then blessed are you
if you do these things,
if you follow my example.
The next two verses in that first John passage
pick up on this idea.
Dear friends,
since God so loved us
because the God of the universe
stepped up from the table
and walked to your dirty, stinky feet
and washed them with his bare hands
and wiped them dry
with a garment around his waist,
since God has so loved you,
we also ought to love one another.
No one has ever seen God,
but if we love one another,
God lives in us
and his love is made complete in us.
I love how Esau Macaulay puts it.
He said that kingdom service
is an enacted parable of the gospel.
When we do this,
when we step up
and serve others in sacrificial ways,
when we lay down our priorities
and our preferences
and our comfort
and when we serve others,
it is a way
in which we demonstrate the gospel
to others around us.
No one has ever seen God.
How often do we have this conversation
with people
when we talk to them about Jesus?
Like, well,
if God would just show up
and tell me he's real,
I'd believe him.
It's like us loving people sacrificially
is God showing up
and telling people that he's real.
Us doing the thing
that doesn't make any cultural sense.
Us saying no
to all of the cultural realities
that are like,
don't do that.
This is above you.
This is beyond you.
You are too important for this.
You are too valuable for this.
If we step out beyond that
and we serve those in need,
it is a parable
that preaches the gospel
that demonstrates God's love
to others around us.
Now that you know these things,
once you get them in your bones,
once you understand them fully,
blessed are you if you do them.
It's the second thing
that I think Jesus'
lived parable does for us.
It teaches us
and it equips us
to go out and do the thing
that we've already learned.
And if we're gonna do it,
we have to learn it first.
The parable is a way
of teaching a truth
that we already know.
Just like Jesus served his disciples
to show them
how much God loves them,
we are invited to serve others
because we have come to know
how much God loves us.
And we could get in
a theological argument
about whether this phrase,
I have left you an example
to follow,
whether it means
that you should actually
wash each other's feet.
That's the argument
I get in with people
when they don't wanna come
to the threefold services.
Like he doesn't mean
actually wash people's feet.
He means sacrificially serve.
And I'm like, maybe.
Maybe that's what he means.
Or maybe he means both.
Right?
And I'm not gonna try
and convince you theologically
that you have to participate
in a foot washing service.
But what I'm saying is like,
what if that's what he meant?
What if he meant
sacrificially serve others
and like make a habit
of washing each other's feet
even when it's culturally irrelevant
because it will teach you
how deeply I love you
and love others?
To grow in the ability
to treat others around us,
even our enemies
with sacrificial love
and service.
This takes time.
It's not a practice
that we will fall into
accidentally.
We won't accidentally
become a person
who lays down our life
for others behind closed doors
when there's nothing
in it for us.
Not only does it take time
and attention
to cultivate this type of service,
but it also takes time
and attention
to make sure
we are doing this type of service
out of a loving relationship
with Christ
and not out of guilt
or in order to receive credit.
I think most of us
are inspired
by the actions of Christ.
Right?
We look at them
and we're like,
wow, that's really impressive.
I'm inspired by it.
Many of us have even come to know
how much Christ truly loves us
through these actions,
but I think all of us
in the room
have room to grow
in our ability
to follow Christ's example
in serving others this way.
This commentator
I read this week
said this,
there's a form
of religious piety
that utters
a hearty amen
to the most stringent
demands of discipleship,
but which rarely
does anything about them.
And I think
when we look at Jesus
setting an example
for us,
saying I have left
an example
for you to follow.
Many of us
in the room
who have grown up
in church
who love Jesus,
we can read this story
about Jesus
washing the disciples' feet
and he says,
I have left you
an example to follow
and we can say yes
and amen.
But when it comes
to actually doing
something like that,
much more complicated.
So, let's not swing
for the fences,
right?
Let's not commit
to this massive,
like, I'm gonna become
like Jesus tomorrow.
Let's take one step,
follow his example
in one way
this week
and do something
for someone
in close proximity
to you,
behind closed doors
when no one's looking,
something that feels
beneath you.
just follow,
just take Christ
at his word,
follow his example,
do the thing
he invited you to do
just once this week
and see how you feel.
See what it teaches you
about how he loves you
and see how others
might see the example
of Jesus
in you.
I think when we,
I think Sam talked
about this a little bit
last week,
I think when we think
about sacrificially
serving others,
we often flip the script.
And we think,
I'm gonna do something
big and in public
to a person
or a group of people
that I don't have
a relationship with already.
We think about
going to the soup kitchen
or going to
the homeless shelter
or doing this big,
audacious act
outside of our normal circle,
but what if we just
started where we are?
What if we followed
the example of Jesus
and did something
for someone we already love
behind closed doors?
Again,
something that feels
beneath us.
I was prepping
for this sermon
this week
and
I can't really
give a great illustration
because
it might reveal something
that I don't wanna reveal,
but
just had this prompting
inside of me
to do this thing
and it was a thing
that I knew
the person
that I was doing it to
really wanted me to do,
which makes me
wanna do it less,
you know what I mean?
I felt like this person
was like fishing for me
to do something for them
and again,
I'm like,
no,
I'm not gonna do
that thing for you
because you want me
to do that thing for you
and I'm like,
no,
no.
And then this passage
came to my mind,
this sermon
came into my heart.
It's like,
it's actually
that is the thing
that you should probably
do the most,
the thing that you think
you shouldn't do,
is beneath you.
It's like,
what if we did that?
We serve Jesus
in that way
this week.
Jesus starts his example
by serving his friends
in private
before he goes
to the cross
to serve his enemies
in public.
I think that's
an example
we can follow.
We can start
by serving
our friends
in private
and it's in that
reality
where we become
the type of person
who can serve
our enemies
in public.
But I think we start
in the reverse.
We try and swing
for the fences
and do this big thing
for our enemies
in public
when we aren't
being formed
in the person
who does it
for people we love
in private.
Does that make sense?
This is formation.
This is Jesus
forming us
into the person
who can follow
his example
out of sacrificial love,
not out of duty
or religious action.
What if we just
started to become
the type of person
that can do
these things?
Now that you
know these things
you will be blessed
if you do them.
Christ set for us,
Dave you can come on up.
Christ set for us
an example
by washing
his disciples' feet.
He did so
so that we might
truly know
experientially
that we might
understand
in our bones
how much
God loves us.
That we would
come back
to this reality
over and over
and over again
allowing
the love
of God
to wash over us
so that we can
serve out of
an abundance
mindset
that we know
and understand
and it's
as we know
and understand
that we can go
and do
for the right
reasons.
Not the
Michael Scott,
Scranton,
Meredith Palmer,
forget the rest.
Fun Run Race
for the Cure.
Right?
Not this like
look at me
look what I'm
doing.
Not this
I feel guilty
so I should.
This man
the God
of the universe
loves me
so much.
He gave
his life
for me.
I have
all that I need
in Christ
and more
and I can
give that
to others.
Hidden
acts of service
help us
comprehend
God's love
more deeply
and model
God's love
more clearly.
I think that's
what the passage
teaches us
today.
That as we
step out in
faith and
obey Christ's
command that
when we do
these hidden
acts in
private it
helps us
learn more
deeply God's
love and it
helps us
model more
clearly to
others how
much he
loves them.
It both
teaches and
equips.
It is
exactly what
Philippians 2
teaches.
Therefore
if you have
any encouragement
from being
united with
Christ
any comfort
from his
love
if any
common sharing
in the spirit
if any
tenderness
and compassion
then take
then make
my joy
complete by
being like
minded
having the
same love
being one
in spirit
and one
in mind
do nothing
out of selfish
ambition
or vain
conceit
this is a
hard list
of things
to do
how can
we do
them
in humility
value others
above yourself
anybody good
at that
not me
not looking
to your own
interest but to
the interest
of others
anybody good
at that
not me
how do we
do this
in your
relationship
with one
another
have the
same
mindset
as Christ
Jesus
who being
in the very
nature
of God
did not
consider
equality
with God
something
to be
used
to his
own
advantage
do you
hear
this
nothing
is beneath
you
as a follower
of Jesus
because the
very son
of God
stepped down
into human
form
and he
walked
streets
filled
with human
feces
and not
only did
he walk
streets
filled
with human
feces
but the
night
before
he would
go to
the cross
for you
and for
me
he stepped
down
beneath
anything
that anyone
would ever
imagine
that he
would do
and he
washed
that feces
off the feet
of those
who are
going to
betray
him
and deny
in your
relationship
with one
another
have the
same
mindset
as Christ
how do
we do
that
if we
do not
understand
how much
he loves
us
and if we
do not
understand
how much
he loves
that person
who is
betraying
us
who is
denying
us
who is
lying
about
us
who is
manipulating
the situation
for their
own gain
how do
we treat
that person
with love
we look
to the
example
of
Jesus
who stooped
down
and washed
the feet
of Judas Iscariot
hours before
he would
lead a
crew of
soldiers
with a
pocket full
of money
straight to
the place
where Jesus
was
who would
kiss him
on the
cheek
for his
own benefit
own gain
and it's
because
Jesus gave
us that
example
that we
can know
how much
he loved
and we
can know
how much
he loves
the person
that he's
inviting us
to serve
whether they
deserve it
or not
whether
we're going
to get
any benefit
or gain
from it
or not
have the
same
mindset
as Christ
Jesus
who being
the very
nature
of God
did not
consider
equality
with God
something
to be
used
to his
own
advantage
rather
he made
himself
nothing
by taking
the very
nature
of a
servant
this is
the invitation
of Jesus
this is
the message
we've been
given to
go out
to our
friends
and tell
them about
you want
to know
what it
means
to be
a
Christian
what a
fun
message
to share
right
this is
the invitation
it's not
some
flashy
lights
and fog
this is
awesome
come be
a part
of this
cool
community
of
people
that
are
trendy
and
doing
cool
things
and
in
unique
ways
no
it's
have
the
same
mindset
of
Christ
who being
in the
very nature
of God
laid down
his
life
this is
the invitation
and who
is going
to receive
that invitation
unless they
have first
known how
much Jesus
loves
them
may we
know
experientially
in our
bones
as we
look to
the
example
of
Jesus
as we
look
to
what
he
did
for
his
disciples
may we
know
how much
he loves
us
so that
we can
do
this
follow
his
example
have
his
mindset
out of
an
abundance
not
scarcity
mindset
we have
all
that we
need
in
Jesus
being
made
in
human
likeness
and being
found
in
appearance
as
man
he
humbled
himself
by
becoming
obedient
to
death
even
on
the
cross
I love
that
these
two
examples
are
back
to
it is
serving
his
friends
in
private
and
serving
his
enemies
in
public
and I
think
as
followers
of
Jesus
if
we're
going
to
be
the
type
of
people
who
in
public
can
follow
the
example
of
Jesus
who
on
the
cross
as
he's
being
crucified
says
father
forgive
them
for
they
do
not
know
what
they
are
doing
if
we
are
going
to
be
the
type
of
people
that
can
live out
that
example
in
public
we
have
to
start
by
becoming
the
person
who
does
this
to
our
friends
in
private
imagine
how
this
attitude
might
affect
our
lives
relationships
in
our
community
imagine
if we
became
a
people
who
knew
God's
love
experientially
not just
intellectually
we knew
it
in our
bones
and because
we knew
it in
our bones
we
demonstrated
it
we followed
his example
and we
gave it
to others
not for
our own
gain
not to earn
some
favor
before God
because there's
no more
favor we can
earn
before God
but we
just
demonstrated
it
imagine
how that
might
impact
the people
who don't
yet know
Jesus
when they
see us
doing this
very thing
for them
that's the
only way
anybody's
going to
respond
yes
to
hey
come
deny
yourself
and follow
Jesus
with us
the only way
somebody says
yes to
that is
when they
understand
how beautiful
Jesus
is
and
1 John
4 says
the way
they
understand
how
beautiful
Jesus
is
when
we
show
up
and
be
Jesus
to
them
and
if
we're
going to
become
a people
who can
do
that
we have
to
first
allow
him
to do
it
for
us
imagine
how much
more
clearly
God's
kingdom
will be
visible
in our
community
if we
learn
to
serve
others
the way
our
master
has
served
us
won't
happen
overnight
however
we can
begin
this
week
with
one
act
of
sacrificial
love
towards
someone
close
to
us
in
private
don't
do
it
for
credit
don't
do
it
out
of
guilt
just
look
to
Jesus
our
example
the
author
and
perfecter
of
our
faith
who
looking
beyond
the
earthly
realities
waiting
to go
to the
Father
did
this
same
knowing
that
we
are
living
for
a
future
kingdom
and
a
future
hope
that
has
far
greater
rewards
than
whatever
we
can
have
here
on
this
earth
let's
pray
Father
in
heaven
thank
you
so
much
for
the
example
of
Jesus
for
the
incarnation
flesh
and
blood
in
the
beginning
was
the
word
or
became
flesh
so
we
could
understand
how
much
you
truly
love
us
not
just
intellectually
from words
on a
page
but
experientially
from a
human
a
God
man
who
washes
feet
and goes
to the
cross
for the
joy
set
before
people
that
know
how
much
you
love
us
filled
with
joy
and
hope
thanksgiving
because
you
love
us
not
because
we
deserve
it
not
because
we
earn
it
not
because
we
can
pay
you
back
for
it
but
because
you
in
your
very
nature
are
God
of
love
God
may
we
know
how
much
you
love
us
and
with
joy
and
excitement
may
we
follow
your
example
and
lay
down
our
lives
for
others
knowing
that
nothing
is
beneath
us
as
kingdom
servants
you
want
to
be
like
your
master
do
as
the
master
did
you
want
to
debate
over
who's
the
greatest
in
the
kingdom
greatest
in
the
kingdom
is
one
who
stoops
down
and
washes
feet
God
remind
us
of
that
and
equip
live
that
way
in
our
community
for
your
glory
for
our
good
for
the
good
of
our
neighbor
in
Jesus
name
I
pray
amen
if
you
stand
with
me
we're
gonna
conclude
the
service
with
a
Scripture
reading
I
went
to
the
conference
I
went
to
was
in
a
liturgical
church
with
like
foot
ceilings
and
we
read
Scripture
out
loud
together
and
it
just
inspired
me
to
just
you
know
let's
do
a
little
bit
of
liturgy
on
our
way
out
today
does
that
sound
good
so
there's
three
slides
I
will
read
the
first
slide
you
will
meditate
on it
the
second
slide
will
be
read
by
you
and
the
third
slide
will
be
read
think
this
passage
really
is
a
prayer
for
us
to
know
God's
love
good
of
our
community
for
this
reason
I
kneel
before
the
father
from
whom
every
family
in
heaven
on
earth
derives
its
name
I
pray
so
that
Christ
may
dwell
in
our
hearts
through
faith
and
I
pray
that
we
being
rooted
and
established
in
love
may
have
power
together
with
all
the
Lord's
holy
people
to
grasp
how
wide
and
how
long
and
how
high
and
how
deep
is
the
love
of
Christ
and
to
know
able
to
do
immeasurably
more
than
all
we
ask
or
imagine
according
to
his
power
that
is
at
work
within
us
amen
go
in
peace
church
you